A Finding Aid to the Phyllis Mark Papers, circa 1939-1978
Archives of American Art
Phyllis Mark papers
circa 1939-1978
Archives of American Art
Mark, Phyllis, 1921-2004
AAA.markphyl
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of sculptor Phyllis Mark measure 1.0 linear feet and date from circa 1939 to 1978. Found are artworks, biographical materials, correspondence including with Fritz Glarner, notes, personal business records, and photographs of Mark and others and of works of art.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of sculptor Phyllis Mark measure 1.0 linear feet and date from circa 1939 to 1978. Found are artworks, biographical materials, correspondence including with Fritz Glarner, notes, personal business records, and photographs of Mark and others and of works of art.
Biographical / Historical
Phyllis Mark (1921-2004) was a sculptor active in New York City, New York. She is known for kinetic sculpture and later transformed her pieces as ready-to-wear jewelry and executed a number of large-scale works.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Phyllis Mark donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in 1977 and 1978.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Women artists; Women sculptors; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Glarner, Fritz, 1899-1972
- Phyllis Mark Papers, circa 1939-1978; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Artworks include three illustrated notebooks of ink sketches and notes, and scattered pencil sketches. Biographical material consists of resumes and a title card for a work of art. Correspondence is with family and friends including Fritz and Lucie Glarner and Judith Rothschild, institutions, and museums. Scattered notes include one notebook. Personal business records contain price lists, sales records, and receipts for materials. Photographs include portraits of Mark with her sculpture, and snapshots of Mark as a young woman, with her family and friends, and at events. Also found are photographs of works of art and of exhibitions, many of which are labeled and annotated. Printed materials focus on Mark's career and include clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and periodicals.
  - Artwork, Sketches, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, Illustrated Notebooks, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Material, 1972-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Glarner, Fritz and Lucie, 1955-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Rothschild, Judith, 1959-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, General, 1955-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Notebook and Notes, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal Business Records, 1969-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, Portraits of Phyllis Mark, 1964-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, Snapshots of Mark with Family and Friends, circa 1939-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Works of Art, 1957-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1950s-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - Printed Material, Periodicals, 1969-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18-19)